Finding Aid for League of Women Voters of Allen Park records, 1955-1986
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
League of Women Voters of Allen Park records 1955-1986
League of Women Voters of Allen Park.
90146 Bm 2
The League of Women Voters of Allen Park was established as a provisional league in 1955, formally recognized in 1956, and operated until 1986 when it merged with the Downriver League of Women Voters. Annual meeting and board meeting minutes and reports, 1955-1986; member newsletters, 1955-1986; topical files comprising committee minutes, reports, position statements, correspondence, pamphlets, and other publications. Subjects covered by files include municipal, county, state, and national elections, and social, political, and environmental issues.
3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was received from the organization (donor no. 7741 ) on November 15, 1989.
The record group is open to research.
The League of Women Voters is a non-partisan volunteer organization whose purpose is to promote political responsibility through the informed and active participation of citizens in government. The League's major activity is voter education; before most elections the League publishes a Voters Guide with information about the candidates and the various ballot proposals. The League also takes action is support of, or in opposition to, selected governmental issues. It does not support or oppose candidates, nor does it support or oppose political parties.
The Allen Park League was organized as a provisional league in 1955; in 1956 this provisional association was formally recognized as the League of Women Voters of Allen Park. In 1984 the Allen Park League investigated the possibility of merging with the Dearborn-Dearborn Heights League but decided against this action. In 1986, however, the Allen Park League ceased to operate as an independent chapter, merging instead with the Downriver Wayne County League of Women Voters which comprised League chapters from the towns of Southgate, Riverview, Trenton, Woodhaven, Wyandotte, and Grosse Ile.
The records of the Allen Park League of Women Voters consist of annual meeting and board meeting minutes and reports, 1955-1986; member newsletters, 1955-1986; topical files comprising committee minutes, reports, position statements, correspondence, pamphlets, and other publications. Subjects covered by files include municipal, county, state, and national elections, and social, political, and environmental issues. The records have been arranged into two series: Administrative Files and Topical Files. Although a wide range of issues of concern to the League's members in the 1960s and 1970s are represented in these files, the documentation of local politics and elections, social services, and environmental issues is particularly strong. As such, these files provide a detailed account of the issues raised by the growth of Allen Park from a small village into a suburban city between 1955 and 1986.
Subjects:
Allen Park (Mich.); Allen Park (Mich.)--Charters.; Allen Park (Mich.)--Politics and government.; City planning--Michigan--Allen Park.; Elections--Michigan--Allen Park.; Environmental protection--Michigan--Allen Park.; League of Women Voters of Allen Park.; Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Municipal government--Michigan.; Schools--Michigan--Allen Park.; Wayne County (Mich.); Women--Michigan--Allen Park--Societies and clubs.
- Administrative Files
  The Administrative Files span the years 1955 to 1986. Files documenting the organization of the provisional League in 1955-1956 are followed by three major sets of files: Annual Meeting Minutes and Reports, 1956-1985; Board Meeting Minutes and Reports, 1956-1985; and a run of the League's "Allen Park Voter" Newsletter, 1955-1986.
  - Provisional League, Board Meeting Minutes 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - Provisional League, Recognition Report 1956 (Box 1)
  - Annual Meeting Minutes and Reports 1956-1985, 22 folders (Box 1)
  - Board Meeting Minutes 1956-1986, 15 folders (Box 1)
  - The "Allen Park Voter" Newsletter 1955-1986, 13 folders (Box 2)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files comprise one series of alphabetically arranged subject files which document all aspects of the League's activities between 1955 and 1986. The bulk of these files document local issues at the municipal and county levels: included are materials generated by several committees of the Allen Park and Detroit Metropolitan Leagues (Housing Action Committee, Metro Integration Study Committee); studies of Allen Park (Charter Revision, Library Services, Recreational Facilities); and studies of Wayne County (Wayne County Home Rule Study). To a lesser extent, these files document state issues (State Constitutional Convention); as well as national and international issues.
  - Annual Reports (Allen Park) 1961, 1976-1978, 1981, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Bylaws and Membership (Allen Park) 1958-1986 (Box 2)
  - Candidate Profiles (Allen Park) 1957-1966 A-Z, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Charter Revision Study (Allen Park) 1966-1970 (Box 2)
  - Citizenship Test 1965-1967 (Box 2)
  - Detroit Metro Area Problems Study 1958-1961 (Box 2)
  - Detroit Metro Area LWV, Annual Conventions 1973-1984, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Detroit Metro Area LWV, Board Meeting Minutes and Newsletter 1973-1985 (Box 2)
  - Education and School Finance Issues 1970, 1977, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Environmental Issues 1964-1984 (Box 3)
  - Finance Committee (Metro Detroit) 1963-1965 (Box 3)
  - Housing Action Committee (Metro Detroit) 1972-1976, 1980 (Box 3)
  - International Relations Issues (United States) 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - Judicial System (Wayne County, State of Michigan) 1967-1975, 1978 (Box 3)
  - "Know Your Allen Park" Publication 1956, 1975 (Box 3)
  - "Know Your Wayne County Government" Committee and Publication 1960-1962, 1974-1975 (Box 3)
  - Lake Erie Basin Committee 1962-1979 (Box 3)
  - LWV United States, National Convention 1970, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Library Services Study (Allen Park) 1960 (Box 3)
  - Metro Integration Study Committee (Detroit Metro Area) 1970-1973 (Box 3)
  - Political Issues 1965-1981 (Box 3)
  - Program Recommendations (Local and National) 1956-1969 (Box 3)
  - Recreation Facilities Study (Allen Park) 1957-1959 (Box 3)
  - Rouge River Basin Committee 1972-1979, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Social Issues 1963-1972 (Box 3)
  - State Constitutional Convention (Michigan) 1958-1962 (Box 3)
  - State Legislators' Interviews 1961-1962, 1972-1977 (Box 3)
  - Taxation (Michigan) 1971-1972, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Transportation (State of Michigan) 1974 (Box 3)
  - Urban Crisis Committee (Detroit Metro) 1973, 1976-1979 (Box 3)
  - Voter Services
    - Miscellaneous 1955-1957 (Box 3)
    - 1957-1983, 1986, 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Wastewater Management (Detroit Metro) 1978, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Wayne County Home Rule Study 1962-1981 (Box 3)
  - Women's Issues and Equal Rights Amendment 1975, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Yearbooks (Allen Park) 1959-1965 (Box 3)
  - Youth Services Study (Allen Park) 1967-1974 (Box 3)